<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Psalmes of inuocation vpon God to preserue her Maiestie and the people of this lande, from the power of our enemies. Collected and gathered togither, by Christopher Stile.</title>
            <title>Psalmes of invocation upon God.</title>
            <author>Stile, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105782</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841508</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841508</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6094</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6094)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 717:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Psalmes of inuocation vpon God to preserue her Maiestie and the people of this lande, from the power of our enemies. Collected and gathered togither, by Christopher Stile.</title>
                  <title>Psalmes of invocation upon God.</title>
                  <author>Stile, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, dwelling in Distaffe Lane, neare the signe of the Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms. --  Selections. --  English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6094:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:6094:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Pſalmes of Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon God, To preſerue her Maieſtie and the people of this lande, from the power of our enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected and gathered togither, by</hi> Chriſtopher Stile.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON </p>
            <p>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, dwelling in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe Lane, neare the ſigne of the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>1588.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Psalms">
            <pb facs="tcp:6094:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6094:2"/>
            <head>Pſalmes of Inuocation vpon God, to preſerue her Maieſtie and the people of this land, from the power of their enemies.</head>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>
                  <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 3. <hi>verſe.</hi> 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>P Lord and helpe vs, O (our God) ſmite all our enemies vpon the cheeke bone, &amp; breake the teeth of the vngodly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 5. 2.</note>Harken thou vnto the voice of our calling, our king and our God: for vnto thee do we make our praier.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe. 8.</note>
                  <hi>Lead vs O Lord in thy righteouſnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our enemies: make thy way plaine before our face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 9.</note>For there is no faithfulnes in their mouthes: their inward parts are verie wickednes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 10.</note>
                  <hi>Their throate is an open ſepulchre: they flatter with their tongue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 11.</note>Deſtroie thou them O God, let them periſh through their owne imaginations: caſt them out in the multitude of their vngodlines, for they haue rebelled againſt thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 6. v. 4.</note>
                  <hi>Turne thee O Lord and deliuer our ſoules, oh ſaue vs for thy mercies ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 6.</note>Stand vp O Lord, in thy wrath, and lift vp thy ſelfe, becauſe of the indignation of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: Ariſe vp for vs in thy iudgement that thou
<pb facs="tcp:6094:3"/>
haſt commanded.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 6. v. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>(Then) all our enemies ſhal be confounded, and ſore vexed: they ſhal be turned backe and put to ſhame ſodeinly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 9. v. 13.</note>Haue mercie vpon vs, O Lord, conſider the trouble which wee ſuffer of them that hate vs: thou that lifteſt vs vp from the gates of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 14.</note>
                  <hi>That we may ſhew all thy praiſes within the ports of the daughter of</hi> Sion: <hi>we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in thy ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 15.</note>(Let) the Antichriſtian power bee ſuncke down, in the pit that they haue made: in the ſame net which they hid priuily, let their feete be taken.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 9. v. 19.</note>
                  <hi>Vp Lord, and let not man haue the vpper hand: let the Heathen be iudged in thy ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 20.</note>Put them in feare (O Lord) that they may know themſelues to be but men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 17. v. 8.</note>
                  <hi>Keepe vs as the apple of an eye: hide vs vnder the ſhadow of thy winges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 9.</note>From the vngodly that trouble vs: our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies compaſſe vs round about, to take away our ſoules.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 10.</note>
                  <hi>They are cloſed in their own fat: and their mouthes ſpeake proud things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 11.</note>They lie waiting in our waie on euerie ſide: turning their eies downe to the ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 12.</note>
                  <hi>Like as a Lion that is greedie of his praie: and as it were a Lions whelpe lurking in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 13.</note> Vp Lord, diſappoint them, and caſt them downe: deliuer our ſoules from the vngodlie
<pb facs="tcp:6094:3"/>
which is a ſword of thine, and keepe vs from the pride of the bloudie Spaniardes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 2. Pſal. 7. 1.</note>
                  <hi>Preſerue vs O God: for in thee haue we put our truſt, and ſaue vs from all them that perſecute vs, and deliuer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 132. v. 1. Pſal. 140. 1.</note>Lord remember our Queene Eliſabeth, in all her troubles: and preſerue her from the wicked man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 4.</note>
                  <hi>O keepe her O Lord from the handes of the vngodlie: preſerue her from the wicked men which ar purpoſed to ouerthrowe her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> Glorie be to the father, and to the ſonne, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 25. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VNto thee, O Lord, doe wee lift vp our ſoules, our God, wee haue put our truſt in thee: O let vs not be confounded, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let our enemies, triumph ouer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 5.</note>Call to remembrance, O Lord, thy tender mercies: and thy louing kindneſſe which hath bin euer of olde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 6.</note>
                  <hi>Remember not the ſinnes and offences of our youth or time paſt: but according to thy mercie thinke vpon vs (O Lord) for thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 15.</note>Turne thee vnto vs, and haue mercy vpon vs: for we are deſolate and in miſerie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 16.</note>
                  <hi>The ſorrowes of our hearts are enlarged:</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6094:4"/>
                  <hi>O bring vs out of our troubles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 17.</note>Looke vpon our aduerſitie and miſerie: and forgiue vs all our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 18.</note>
                  <hi>Conſider our enemies how many they are: and they beare a tirannous hate againſt vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 19.</note>O keepe our ſoules and deliuer vs, let vs not be confounded: for we haue put our truſt in thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 27. 1.</note>
                  <hi>Thou Lord art our light and our ſaluation, whom then ſhall we feare: thou Lord art the ſtrength of our life, of whom ſhal we be afraid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 3.</note>Though an hoaſt of men were laide againſt vs, yet ſhall not our hearts be afraied: and though there riſe vp warre againſt vs; yet will we put our truſt in thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 8.</note>
                  <hi>Harken vnto our voice, O Lord, when wee cry vnto thee: haue mercy vpon vs &amp; here vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. v. 10.</note>O hide not thou thy face from vs: nor caſt vs thy ſeruants away in diſpleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 11.</note>
                  <hi>Thou haſt been our ſuccour: leaue vs not, neither forſake vs O God of our ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 12. and 14.</note>Teach vs thy way; O Lord, and lead vs in the right way becauſe of our enemies: and deliuer vs not ouer vnto the will of our aduerſaries.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 28. 2.</note>
                  <hi>Heare the voice of our humble petitions when wee crie vnto thee: when wee hold vp our hands toward the mercy ſeat of thy holie temple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Rewarde our enemies according to their deedes: and according to the wickednes of their owne inuentions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recompence them after the workes of their</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6094:4"/>
                  <hi>owne hands: paie them that they haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 31. 5.</note>Draw vs out of the net that they haue laide priuily for vs: for thou art our ſtrength.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 28. 9.</note>
                  <hi>The Lorde is our ſtrength: and hee is the wholeſome defence of his Queene.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 33. 18.</note>Deliuer our ſoules from death: and feede vs in the time of dearth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 19.</note>
                  <hi>Our ſoules haue paciently tarried for the Lord: for he is our helpe and our ſhield.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe. 20.</note>Our heart ſhall reioyce in him: becauſe wee haue hoped in his holie name.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 21.</note>
                  <hi>Let thy mercifull kindnes (O Lord) be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs: like as we do put our truſt in thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. v. 17</note>O doe well vnto thy ſeruant Queene Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth: that ſhee may liue, and keepe thy word.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 109. 26.</note>
                  <hi>Helpe her, O Lord our God, oh ſaue her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy mercy.</hi> Gloriebe to the father, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <head>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 35. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PLead thou our cauſe, O Lord, with them that ſtriue with vs: &amp; fight thou againſt them that fight againſt vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 2</note>Laie hand vpon the ſhield and buckler: and ſtand vp to helpe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 3</note>
                  <hi>Bring forth the ſpeare, and ſtop the way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that perſecute vs: ſaie vnto our ſoules I am thy ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 4.</note>Let them bee confounded and put to ſhame
<pb facs="tcp:6094:5"/>
that ſeeke after our ſoules: let them be turned back and brought to confuſion, that imagine miſchiefe for vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 5.</note>
                  <hi>Let them be as duſt before the winde: and the Angell of the Lord ſcattring them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 6.</note>Let their way be darke and flippery: and let the Angell of the Lord perſecute them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 7.</note>
                  <hi>For they haue priuily laide their net to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs without a cauſe: yea, euen without a cauſe haue they made a pit for our ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 8.</note>Let a ſodeine deſtruction come vpon them vnawares, and the net that they haue laide priuily catch themſelues: that they may fall into their owne miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 23.</note>
                  <hi>Awake and ſtand vp to iudge our quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell: auenge thou our cauſe our God and our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 24.</note>Iudge vs, O Lord our God, according to thy righteouſnes: and let them not triumph ouer vs thy Engliſhnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 25.</note>
                  <hi>Let not the Antichriſtians ſaie in their hearts, there, there, ſo would we haue it: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let the</hi> Spaniard <hi>ſay, wee haue deuoured them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 26.</note>Let them be put to confuſion and ſhame togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that reioyce at our trouble: let them bee clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with rebuke and diſhonour that boaſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 9.</note>
                  <hi>Deliuer vs from all our offences: &amp; make vs not a rebuke vnto the fooliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 13.</note>Heare our praiers, O Lord, and with thine
<pb facs="tcp:6094:5"/>
eares conſider our calling: holde not thy peace at our teares.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 38. 21.</note>
                  <hi>Forſake vs not, O Lord our God: bee not thou far from vs thy Engliſhnation, haſt thee to helpe vs: O Lord God our ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 38. 19.</note>For our enemies liue and are mightie: and they that hate vs wrongfully are many in number.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 40. 21.</note>
                  <hi>But thou art our helper and redeemer: make no long tarrying O our God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 16.</note>Let it bee thy pleaſure to deliuer vs: make haſt (O Lord) to helpe vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 44. 4.</note>
                  <hi>Thou art our king, O God ſend helpe vnto thy Engliſh</hi> Iacob.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 26.</note>Ariſe and helpe vs: and deliuer vs for thy mercies ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 53. 3.</note>
                  <hi>For ſtrangers are riſen vp againſt vs: and tirants (which haue not thee O God before their eies) ſeeke after our ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 1.</note>Saue vs O God for thy names ſake: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge vs in thy ſtrength.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 59. 17. Pſal. 60. 4.</note>
                  <hi>Vnto thee our ſtrength will wee ſing: for thou, O God, art our refuge and our merciful God, and wee will dwell in thy tabernacle for euer: and our truſt ſhal be vnder the couering of thy wings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 61. 6.</note>Graunt our Queene O Lord, a long life: that her yeares may endure with vs the full courſe of nature, and with thee for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 121. 8</note>
                  <hi>Preſerue O Lord, her going out, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in: from this time forth, for euermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Glorie be to the Father, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Psalm">
               <pb facs="tcp:6094:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 119. <hi>verſe</hi> 153.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 143. 9. Pſal. 108. 12.</note>
                  <hi>O Conſider our aduerſitie and deliuer vs O Lord: from all our enemies, for wee flee vnto thee to hide vs: for vain is the helpe of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. verſ. 15. 4. Pſal. 144. 2.</note>Auenge thou our cauſe and deliuer vs: quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vs according vnto thy word, for thou art our helpe and our fortreſſe, our caſtle, &amp; deliuerer, and our defendor, in whom we truſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 108. 13.</note>
                  <hi>Vnto thee lift we vp our eies: O thou that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 123. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>dwelleſt in the heauens: through thee can we doe great actes: it is thou that ſhalt treade downe our enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 142. 7.</note>Heare vs O Lord and that ſoone, for our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit waxeth faint: hide not thy face from vs thy Engliſhnation, leſt wee be like vnto them that goe downe into the pit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 123. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Haue mercy vpon vs O Lord, for our ſoules are filled with the ſcornfull reproofe of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian rout: and with the deſpightfulnes of the proud Spaniards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 140. 2.</note>They imagine miſchiefe in their hearts: and ſtir vp ſtrife all the daie long.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 120. 6.</note>
                  <hi>We haue laboured vnto them for peace, but when wee ſpeake vnto them thereof: they make them readie to battaile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 140. 6.</note>Then wee ſaide vnto the Lord, thou art our God, heare the voice of our praiers O Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6094:6"/>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 140. 7.</note>
                  <hi>O Lord God, thou ſtrength of our health: thou haſt couered our heads in the day of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 8.</note>Let not the vngodlie haue their deſire O Lord: let not their miſchieuous imagination proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, leſt they be too proud.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 9.</note>
                  <hi>Let the miſchiefe of their owne lippes, fall vpon the heads of them: that compaſſe vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the hotte burning coales of thy wrath fall vpon them which trouble vs thine heritage: let them be caſt into the fire of thy iudgement, and into the pit that they neuer riſe vp againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 142. 8.</note>
                  <hi>Send downe thine hand from aboue, and take vs out of the waters of troubles, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from the hands of ſtraunge children: for they are too ſtrong for vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mich. 7. 10.</note>So they that be our enemies ſhall looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and be confounded, which now ſaie where is the Lord their God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 16.</note>
                  <hi>This the Heathen ſhall ſee, &amp; bee aſhamed for all their combined powers: ſo that they ſhal laie their hand vpon their mouth, and ſtop their eares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 17.</note>They ſhall licke the duſt like a ſerpent, and as the woormes of the earth, that tremble in their holes: they ſhall bee afraide of thee O Lorde our God, and they ſhall feare thee much.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Who is ſuch a God as thou, that pardoneſt wickednes, and forgiueſt the offences of the remnant of thine Engliſh heritage? and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6094:7"/>
                  <hi>not thy wrath foreuer: for thy delight is in compaſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 19.</note>Turne thee againe, &amp; be mercifull vnto thine Engliſh Sion: put away all our wickedneſſes and caſt all our ſinnes into the bottom of the ſea.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 144. 10.</note>
                  <hi>O Lord giue ſtil victorie vnto our Queene: and preſerue thy ſeruant Elizabeth from the ſword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 145. 12.</note>That thy power, thy glory, and thy mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, by her may be knowen vnto men: in defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her kingdoms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Sonne, and to the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As it was in the beginning is now; and euer ſhalbe world without end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:6094:7"/>
            <head>A GODLY PRAYER, WHEREIN is deſired aide of God againſt his enimies, forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, and to turne his plagues as well of the ſword as penurie, which be due for ſinne, farre from this land.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord of hoſts, thou God of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, which ſitteſt betweene the Cherubins, that ruleſt all the kingdoms of the world, to whom all powers muſt ſtoupe and obey. Ariſe O Lord, &amp; ſhew forth thy ſelfe, &amp; come forth ſtil to helpe vs, plucke out thy hand out of thy boſome, and draw out thy ſword, and ſmite downe the heathen that riſe vp againſt vs, that ſeeke to puniſh vs, not for our ſinnes, but for the malice they beare againſt thy Goſpel: for thou art God alone, that ruleſt in all the kingdoms of the world, thou ſtilleſt the rage of the ſeas, and makeſt wars to huſh, in all quarters thou quieteſt the madneſſe of the people, thou bringeſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes of the heathen to nought, and makeſt the counſels of the vngodly to be of none effect, thou chaſtiſeſt thy people O Lord becauſe of their ſinne, and then thou ſaieſt, turne againe you chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men, and whenſoeuer any people doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent them of their ſins and harken vnto thy heſts, thou wilt put all their wickedneſſe out of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membance, and wilt receiue them vnto thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: thou ſpareſt all thoſe that vnfainedly call vpon thee by true repentance, through a liuely faith in thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. Wherfore (O good
<pb facs="tcp:6094:8"/>
Lord) we here thy beloued people according to our dueties aſſembled together before thy diuine maieſtie, in the name of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, doe ſtill humble our ſelues vnto thee, pouring out our prayers vnto thee for our moſt gracious Queene, our nobles, magiſtrates &amp; gouernors, for our ſelues, and for all the people of this thy land of England: acknowledging and confeſsing from the bottom of our harts, that we haue ſinned, we haue committed iniquitie, we haue liued vniuſtly, we haue done vngodly, in that we haue not regarded thy wholeſom counſel, godly admonitions, and fatherly warnings which thou haſt giuen vs from time to time by thy ſeruants the miniſters of thy holy worde and ſacraments, though that they haue riſen vp earely and late to exhort, intreate, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech vs in thy name to forſake our ſinnes and be reconſiled vnto thee: ſtill wee haue followed the imaginations of our owne harts, hardening our faces as an Adamant againſt thee and thy worde, to prouoke thy great wrath and heauie diſpleaſure againſt this our natiue countrie of England, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelues. If thou O Lord ſhouldeſt marke what is done amiſſe, and conſider our ſins and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities according to our deſerts, it would be to our vtter ouerthrow &amp; confuſion, and not onely cauſe thee to plague vs, in perſecuting, troubling, and moleſting vs by the ſword of forren power ſtirred vp againſt vs by the Romiſh antechriſt the Pope, many and ſundrie waies to our great trouble and coſt, to the diſquieting of our bodies, and expence
<pb facs="tcp:6094:8"/>
of our goods by ſea and land, but alſo to ſtrike vs with many plagues of ſicknes diſeaſes and penurie, if thou ſhouldeſt conſider our ſinnes. Wherefore O Lord our God, we doe moſt humblie beſeech thee to be good and gratious vnto vs, &amp; that thou wilt vouchſafe to turne all thy diſpleaſure from vs and to forgiue vs all our ſinnes paſt, and graunt that wee may liue better in thy obedience hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then hetherto we haue done. And although we haue ſinned O Lord, yea grieuouſly ſinned, and our ſinnes do witneſſe againſt vs, yet we know that thou art a righteous iudge, and ſpareſt when we deſerue puniſhment, and in the middeſt of thy wrath thinkeſt vpon mercie: Spare vs therefore good Lord we beſeech thee, and let not thy people of England thine heritage be brought to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But as thou haſt ſtood vp for vs and fought our battailes hitherto, ſo we pray thee deare Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſtill be our defence and ſuccour againſt all our enimies. Thou art our mercifull Father through Ieſus Chriſt, for whoſe ſake wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to be mercifull vnto vs, and forgiue vs all our ſinnes, and turne thy direfull anger from vs. We the people of England are thy people O Lord, and thou art our God: we are thy flocke, and thou art our ſhepeheard: we are thy children, and thou art our Father. Be merciful vnto vs thy children: tender vs thy flocke, and defend vs thy Engliſhna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Turne thy wrath vpon the nations that haue not knowne thee, and that doe not call vpon thy name: and turne it we pray thee vpon the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians
<pb facs="tcp:6094:9"/>
hoſt, ſend forth thine angel ſtil to ſcatter them, as ſometime thou didſt in the hoſt of <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib</hi> for <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Hezechiah</hi> in his time. Let the blaſt of the trumpers blowne by our <hi>Gedeon,</hi> ſtill ſtrike a terror in the harts of the Antechriſtian Madianites, with their combined powers, and let be hard the ſounding of thy hoſt in the aire to the amaſing of the Spaniſh Aſſyrians, that they and theirs may be a pray for our <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and our Engliſh hoſt? or ſinke them in the ſea as thou didſt <hi>Pharao</hi> &amp; his hoſt in purſuing thy Iſrael, to bring them into their ſeruitude, that ſo our <hi>Elizabeth</hi> &amp; all her faithfull ſubiects may ſing the ſonges of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph to thy diuine maieſtie, that giueſt victorie to Kinges. And further we beſeech thee deare Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, that as thou haſt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſent vs plentie and encreaſe vpon the earth, ſo giue vs a happie ingathering of the ſame, to thy glorie and our comfort, and giue vs grace by thy fauourable puniſhments to amend our liues, and make vs thankeful (good Lord) for all thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhewed vpon vs from time to time, and for the diſcomforting of our enimies in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whereto we beſeech thee riſe vp on hie ſtill to ride on, and to fight our battels by ſea and by land, to the vtter ouerthrow of the Antechriſtian po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, to the ſhame of al thoſe that hate thy goſpel, and to thy glorie and our comfort, through Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, to whom with thee and the holy ghoſt be all glorie, power, and dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS. </trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>C. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6094:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
